Guide to the Division of Social Work, Marion Hathway Files, University of Pittsburgh, 1930-1938 UA.90.18.1
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- County Welfare Bill, December 1933-June 1935 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  County Welfare Organization in Pennsylvania A County Welfare Plan for Pennsylvania Extensive materials regarding the development and lobbying for state legislation in public welfare in Pennsylvania.
- D - General Correspondence, February 1933-June 1938 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Department of Public Welfare, August 1935-September 1937 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  Newspaper clipping (undated and without identification of the newspaper) reporting that "Four city welfare department employees are going to school on city time…" "All are social workers." One is to attend Duquesne University and three are to attend the University of Pittsburgh; Organizational chart of Social Service Department of "Pittsburgh DPW"; "Notes on former students"
- de Schweinitz, Karl, Secretary of the Pennsylvania Department of Public Assistance, April 1936-April 1938 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Division of Social Work – Curriculum and Related Materials, 1932-1938 (Box 2, Folder 65-70)
- Dunham, Arthur, June 1933-March 1938 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  Arthur Dunham was Secretary for Family Welfare and Relief Division of the Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania. Mr. Dunham also appears to have had affiliations with the New York School of Social Work, the University of Michigan and the Russell Sage Foundation. Included here is the following: "Getting Things Done" by Arthur Dunham reprinted from The Survey, April 15, 1928; "Shoes – and Ships – and Sealing Wax-" by Arthur Dunham reprinted from The Survey Mid-Monthly, April, 1931; Reprint The Social Worker and the Scissors; 4. Reprint Fourteen Points for Dictators; Extensive correspondence covering a course in "Problems in Social Welfare Administration," the accreditation of the social work program at the University of Pittsburgh, the training of public employees for the state, the publication of Pennsylvania Social Work, the Federation of Agencies, the Pennsylvania Conference on Social Work, the Public Charities Association of Pennsylvania, and pending legislation concerning public welfare in Pennsylvania; A March 17, 1938 letter from Dr. Hathway to Dunham in which she informs him that without his permission, she is suggesting his name for the new post of Dean of Social Work at the University of Pittsburgh
- E - General Correspondence, November 1932 to June 1938 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  Correspondence regarding meetings, publications, classes, personnel references, the "Emergency Peace Campaign," developments in other states, requests for information from members of Congress, etc.
  In one major letter dated March 2, 1934, Dr. Hathway traces the history of the social work program at the University of Pittsburgh from 1918 to 1934. It contains the best and most authoritative summary known to exist.
- Educational Policies Commission, February 1936-March 1938 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  Letter inviting Dr. Hathway (addressed as "Mr. Marion Hathway") to serve as an ex officio consultant to the Commission; Various pamphlets and press releases concerning the Commission's work.
- Elmer, Manuel C., March 1933–March 1938 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  A March 9, 1933 memorandum from Elmer to the "Members of the Division of Social Work" outlining the steps Elmer thought necessary for the development of the Division. It is far ranging and includes curriculum, research, library, fund raising, and a variety of policies; Correspondence covering Elmer's efforts to obtain funding from the Buhl Foundation; Other miscellaneous correspondence regarding courses, instructors, salaries, tuition, etc. See also Folder 201, Teagarden.
- Emergency Relief, March 1927-May 1934 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  Extensive correspondence with state agencies and universities in 21 states regarding the training of emergency relief workers, their salaries, and other details of emergency aid during the depression before the passage of the Social Security Act; There are letters from Frank Bruno at Washington University, Margaret Leal at the New York School of Social Work, Katherine Hardwick at Simmons, James Cutler at Western Reserve University and others.
- Extension School, Erie, July 1935–November 1937 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  Course listings; Students; Roster of social workers in Erie, PA; The Erie Chapter of the American Association of Social Workers.
- Extension School General, October 1934–February 1938 (Box 3, Folder 77-78)
  Brochure of extension courses for the 1934-1935 academic year; Correspondence documenting the offering of extension courses in at least Beaver Falls, Brookville (Jefferson County), Butler, Erie, Johnstown, Kittanning and Mercer; Information on enrollment, courses and students; Responses to questionnaire.
- Extension School, Washington, February 1935–October 1936 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  Correspondence about and description of two courses offered in Washington, PA.
- F – General Correspondence, February 1935 – October 1936 (Box 3, Folder 80)
- Faculty Personnel Data Sheets, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 81)
- Family and Child Welfare Committee, Pennsylvania Charities Association, May 1938-April 1939 (Box 3, Folder 82)
- Family Society of Allegheny County, July 1935–June 1938 (Box 3, Folder 83)
- Federation of Social Agencies, February 1937-May 1938 (Box 3, Folder 85-86)
  Discussions of a number if issues including the report of the "Committee on Free Speech and Assemblage," Article Hathway submitted in 1937 for inclusion in "The Federator," the newsletter of the Federation of Social Agencies. Courses in Psychiatry of Juvenile Delinquency, Psychology of Juvenile Delinquency, The Problem of Mental Disease, Child Psychiatry, Group Work, Local Public Welfare Administration and others are mentioned.
- Fellowships and Scholarships, February 1934-February 1938 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  Correspondence from the New York School of Social Work regarding criteria for admission and list of questions asked of applicants; Correspondence with Sophonisba Breckinridge (University of Chicago), Virginia Robinson (Pennsylvania School of Social Work), Gordon Hamilton (New York School of Social Work); Announcement of 1937 summer training courses offered at Henry Street Settlement in New York City; Announcements of various fellowships and scholarships; Lists of fellowship and scholarship awardees.
- Federal Emergency Relief Administration, January 1934-October 1935 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  Correspondence from Dr. Hathway regarding her doctoral dissertation ("The Migratory Worker and Family Life") completed at the University of Chicago in 1933; Correspondence regarding students and lists of students; Several letters exchanged with the West Virginia Relief Administration which regarding students "assigned" to the University of Pittsburgh.
- Field Trips (Box 3, Folder 88)
  List of agencies being visited by faculty and students including Thorn Hill, Holy Family Orphanage, Mayview, Juvenile Detention Home, Juvenile Court Hearing, IKS; List of "points to be observed and covered" in field visits; Correspondence related to field trips including Polk State School; Lists of students assigned to various agencies for visits.
- Field work Applicants, 1930-1934 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  Lists of students accepted, rejected and placed on lists of alternates for placement in various agencies from 1930 to 1934.
- Field Work Evaluation Forms (Box 3, Folder 90)
- Field Work Evaluation Forms from other Schools (Box 3, Folder 91)
  A Rating Scale for Social Workers from The Family, February, 1934;Evaluation forms from Fordham University, New York School of Social Work, Pennsylvania School of Social Work, Smith College School of Social Work, Western Reserve University, National Catholic School of Social Service, Simmons College School of Social Work, University of Minnesota, University of Southern California, University of Washington, Washington University, Atlanta School of Social Work, University of Chicago, University of Denver
- Field Work -General, 1932-1938 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  One item is dated 1922. It is a report of a "Committee on the Supervision and Training of New Workers"; An undated document with the heading "Medical social field work should give the following particular experiences."; A reprint of an article from July, 1934 in The News-Letter of the American Association of Psychiatric Social Workers entitled "A Training Program in a Family Case Work Agency."; Extensive correspondence, memoranda and policy statements regarding field work, evaluation of field work, student placements and meeting minutes; Proposed Cooperative Plan between Mother's Assistance Fund and Carnegie Institute of Technology; Correspondence with Pennsylvania Training School at Morganza regarding placement of students; List of persons who were employed temporarily for Old Age Assistance investigations; Correspondence regarding individual students; List of employment openings; Information regarding field work objectives and evaluations.
- Field Work Outlines, July 1932-October 1932 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  Information desired in foster home investigation; Visitor's first investigation of foster home; Child guidance clinic outline for social history; Instructions for preparing and presenting papers before the class; Outline for writing up first interview taken from an article by Odencrenz, Louise in The Social Worker
- Field Work Practices Report by Students' Organization in Social Work (Box 3, Folder 94)
- Field Work Questionnaire on Modifications and New Developments (Box 3, Folder 95)
- Field Work Statistics, compiled by Ruth B. Camblon, 1932-1937 (Box 3, Folder 96-98)
- Field Work Student Evaluations (Box 3, Folder 99)
  Various rating forms, guidelines and suggested experiences for field work students and possibly agency workers; One printed form is titled " Report by District Superintendent of Social Case Worker at Time of Recommendation for Increase in Salary and Termination of Probation Period."
- Field Work Student Evaluation Report Blanks (Box 3, Folder 100)
- Field Work Student Evaluation Outlines (Box 3, Folder 101)
- Student Field Work Evaluations, 1st and Second Semesters, 1932-1935 (Box 3, Folder 102-107)
- Student Field Work Evaluations, 1st and 2nd Semesters, 1935-1938 (Box 4, Folder 108-113)
- Student Field Work Evaluations, Summer, 1934-1938 (Box 4, Folder 114-118)
- Field Work Supervision Materials (Box 4, Folder 119)
  Correspondence including with Bertha Reynolds at Smith College; Several reports on field work including "Personality Relationships in Supervision," "Methods of Supervision," "Correlation of Academic Work of the Students with Field Work Experience," "Study of Student Case Records," "Selection of Cases," "Development of Case Recording As a Factor in Supervision," and "Field Work Evaluation."; List of about 37 field work supervisors for May, 1938; Suggested Field Work Objectives and Experiences for First and Second Year Students in a Family Agency.
- Field Work Supervisors, 1933-1937 (Box 4, Folder 120-123)
  Suggested Field Work Objectives and Experiences for First and Second Year Students in a Family Agency; Suggestions on Case-Work Training and Field Supervision; Suggested Program for Supervisor's Conference for Semester February to June, 1935; Supervisors' List for October, 1937; Brief letter to Bertha Reynolds. Committee correspondence, much of it with Ruth Camblon, Field Work Director; Meeting minutes; Survey of field supervisors. Sample forms.
- Finances of Division, Petty Cash Account, November 1937-June 1938 (Box 4, Folder 124)
- G - General Correspondence, October 1932-April 1938 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  Wide variety of correspondence including letters of reference, information about speaking engagements, theses, juvenile and adult corrections, admissions, and student aid; Material regarding the civil service status of Juvenile Court employees in other states and in Allegheny County; Information regarding a "Study of the Care of Dependent Children under the Supervision of the Juvenile Court of Allegheny County."; Dr. Hathway's membership in the "Unemployment Census Committee"; Other miscellaneous correspondence.
- H - General Correspondence, January 1933-June 1938 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  Wide variety of correspondence including references to Porter Lee, Grace Abbott, Mary Wolcott, Harry Hopkins and Dorthea Dix. Dr. Hathway published an article on Dix about January, 1935 in the Western Pennsylvania Historical Magazine; Correspondence regarding admission, financial aid, theses, letters of reference, and YWCA Board activities; Correspondence showing close ties with the Seattle Community Fund; Correspondence regarding a national research study on "supervising children's agencies and institutions." "Supervising" apparently referred to licensing; Correspondence with legislators presenting detailed comments on specific proposed legislation; Correspondence with the City of Pittsburgh "Department of Public Welfare" regarding implementing the Social Security Act; Correspondence showing Dr. Hathway's great interest in unemployment and relief; A newspaper article regarding the "Harmarville Convalescent Home" and it's director Miss Lillian G. McDermitt; Other miscellaneous correspondence.
- Hamilton, Gordon (Box 4, Folder 127)
- Hatch, Mildred (Box 4, Folder 128)
  Access Restrictions
  Restricted: Confidential
- Hill, Lewis B. (Box 4, Folder 129)
  Correspondence between Ruth Gamblon and Dr. Lewis B. Hill regarding lectures Dr. Hill was to give in the area of social psychiatry for graduate students.
- Home and School Visitor Certification (Box 4, Folder 130)
- I - General Correspondence (File-cabinet 131)
- Institutes, 1935-1937 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 132-133)
  Correspondence regarding the presentation at the School o f Social Work of an Institute by Bertha Reynolds on "Supervision" in 1935; Information reading an Institute by Mary E. Hurlbutt of the New York School of Social Work on the topic "Community Program and Nationality Groups" in 1936; Information regarding an Institute by Charoltte Towle in 1936. Records of several institutes sponsored by the Pennsylvania Conference of Social Welfare in Pittsburgh and Philadelphia. Conference programs and attendance included. "Client's Behavior and Worker's Attitudes" was a session led by Ruth B. Camblon of the University of Pittsburgh social work faculty.
- International Institute, 1936-1938 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 134)
  Correspondence with the Service Bureau for Foreign Speaking Peoples of the International Institute of the Young Womens Christian Association in Pittsburgh. (sic) Correspondence includes membership, social events and field placements. The school apparently placed students at the International Institute in at least 1936-1937 and 1937-1938.
- Irene Kaufmann Settlement, October 22, 1937 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 135)
  Copy of a memorandum to Dr. Hathway regarding the detailed arrangements for one student at the Irene Kaufmann Settlement.
- J - General Correspondence, 1933-1938 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 136)
  Correspondence with Arlene Johnson in her role as Assistant Director of the State of Washington Emergency Relief Administration and later as Associate Director of the Graduate Division of Social Work at the University of Washington in Seattle; Correspondence regarding the "supervisory powers of the Bureau of Children."; Correspondence in 1935 "concerning the organization of the New County Relief Boards."; Correspondence with Counsel for the Special Senate Committee to Investigate Unemployment and Relief; Letters of reference, offers of employment, information of admissions and scholarships.
- Jewish Family Welfare Association, March 1934-May 1936 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 137)
  Memo concerning field work plans at Jewish Family Welfare Association; Student lists and evaluations Analysis of September, 1934 JFWA caseload; 1935 Annual Report of the Director of JFWA; Other miscellaneous correspondence and memoranda.
- Jewish Social Service Bureau, 1932-1939 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 138-139)
  Jewish Family Welfare Association service statistics from 1930, 1932 and 1934; Survey of family situations of children in foster homes and institutions in Pittsburgh; Report of the Jewish Service Bureau Staff Committee on Relief; Newsletters of the Jewish Social Service Bureau; Information regarding students placed at the Jewish Family Welfare Association for field work in 1936-1937 and 1937-1938.
- Joint Vocational Service, June 1934-March 1938 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 140)
  Correspondence regarding student field placements at the Joint Vocational Service; Correspondence regarding various candidates for agency and teaching positions; Descriptive information regarding Joint Vocational Service; Other miscellaneous memoranda and correspondence.
- Juvenile Court., October 1931-November 1937 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 141)
  Arrangements for students to visit Juvenile Court; Job announcements and applications; "Recommendations for Selection and Qualifications of Personnel of the New Juvenile Court"; Correspondence with officials in California, Ohio, New York, Wisconsin, New Jersey and Maryland regarding juvenile court personnel practices; Report on training program at the Juvenile Court; Suggestions for a training program at the Juvenile Court; Other miscellaneous memoranda and correspondence
- K - General Correspondence, July 1933-May 1938 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 142)
  Letters of reference; Correspondence regarding student field work assignments; Correspondence regarding accreditation; Correspondence regarding the Social Survey of Pittsburgh with such persons as Paul Kellogg, Phillip Klein and others; Correspondence with Maurice J. Karpf; Other miscellaneous correspondence.
- Kasserman, Margaret (File-cabinet 131, Folder 143)
  Numerous reports of student performance containing confidential case names (Kasserman was a field work supervisor); A handwritten paper entitled "Placement of Physically Handicapped Children in Foster Homes." The paper has no date or author identification, but appears to be student work.
- Klein, Alice C. (File-cabinet 131, Folder 144)
  Correspondence largely concerning examinations for employment in the Department of Public Assistance" and Dr. Hathway's participation as an oral examiner.
- L - General Correspondence, November 1932-May 1938 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 145)
  Correspondence regarding a "Poor Law Conference" in Pittsburgh; Correspondence regarding the need for the local Family Society to affiliate with the Family Welfare Association of America; Correspondence in 1933 with I. Albert Liveright, Secretary of the Pennsylvania Department of Public Welfare, regarding implementation of the new Federal Emergency Relief Administration; Correspondence regarding the Infant Boarding Home Law; Correspondence regarding book orders, invitations to speak, students, a lecture series, and a request to do an investigation of an agency problem in New York City; Correspondence with Virginia Robinson, Assistant Director and Professor of Social Case Work at the Pennsylvania School of Social Work in Philadelphia; Other miscellaneous correspondence.
- Liaison Conference, 1934-1937 (File-cabinet 131, Folder 146-148)
  1934-35: Agenda, minutes, conference participants, presentations and reports with miscellaneous related correspondence.
  1936: Agenda, minutes, conference participants, presentations and reports with miscellaneous related correspondence; Telegram postponing conference on one day's notice because of March, 1936 flood.
  1937: Announcements, correspondence and minutes of a conference held in Harrisburg and attended by representatives of large agencies, schools of social work and the Pennsylvania Department of Public Welfare. The conference concerned the details surrounding the implementation of public assistance and other provisions of the new Social Security Act. One recommendation being debated was "the consolidation of all services in the local community, including Poor Boards, the administration of these services to be placed with a new assistance board, and the supervision and standardization of the work to be assigned to a new state department. … In recommending the abolition of the Poor Boards the report recommends the transfer to the county commissioners of the almshouse property now held by the boards, …"
- Mc – General correspondence, December 1933-February 1938 (Box 5, Folder 149)
  Correspondence regarding admissions, reports, appointments to leadership positions, institutes, conferences, speeches, etc; Correspondence regarding the creation of the Falk Clinic as part of the University Medical School and its possible use for training medical social workers.
- M - General Correspondence, March 1933-May1938 (Box 5, Folder 150)
  Correspondence regarding the National Urban League Fellowship at the University of Pittsburgh, student evaluations, letters of reference, Dorthea Dix, a study of a New York Program for Transient and Homeless people, several conferences, various local and state-wide Community Fund projects, and a 1937 letter acknowledging Dr. Hathway's provision of a child Welfare syllabus to a faculty member at the College of William and Mary
- Meader, LeRoy M. A., October 1935-June 1938 (Box 5, Folder 151)
  Correspondence with Dr. LeRoy Meader, a Philadelphia physician who served as medical director of the Pennsylvania Mental Hygiene Committee. Meader presented several series of lectures in Pittsburgh under the sponsorship of the Division of Social Work funded by the Buhl Foundation; Lists of attendees at Meader's lectures. (Apparently credit was awarded as there are grades and notes regarding incompletes); Newspaper clipping announcing one of the lecture series
- Master Degree Materials and Requirements, January 1936-July 1938 (Box 5, Folder 152-153)
  Summary of the Regulations of the Graduate School, University of Pittsburgh, 1937; Requirements for Master of Arts in Social Work Degree; Schedules and questions for oral examinations; Guidelines for thesis preparation; Oral examination outcomes; Multiple copies of a memorandum to Master of Arts in Social Work students outlining the 8 requirements for the degree.
- The Migratory Worker and Family Life, December 1933-October 1935 (Box 5, Folder 154)
  The file consists of correspondence regarding the publication of Dr. Hathway's doctoral dissertation; Rejection letter from Yale University Press; Correspondence with University of North Carolina Press; Correspondence with the journal, The Family; Correspondence with a literary agent; Correspondence with Edith Abbott; Correspondence with University of Chicago Press, both pre and post publication; Original contract for publication of the dissertation by the University of Chicago press in which the School of Social Service Administration at the University of Chicago agreed to pay the $587.30 cost of publication.
- Miller, Margaret C., March 1937-May 1938 (Box 5, Folder 155)
  Correspondence with and about Margaret Miller who served during much of the period covered by the file as Executive Secretary of the Mothers' Assistance Fund of Allegheny County, the Blind Pension and Old Age Assistance; A partial University of Pittsburgh academic transcript for Margaret Miller from 1931-32 and 1932-33.
- Minutes on Supervisor Seminars, October 1936-May 1937 (Box 5, Folder 156)
  Minutes of supervision seminars at the Allegheny County Emergency Relief Board, the Children's Aid Society, Travelers Aid, Children's Service Bureau, Family Society and Jewish Family Welfare.
- Mothers Assistance Fund, November 1933-December 1937 (Box 5, Folder 157)